Hey, hey, hey.
[Music]
Welcome, Mental Health Monday family.
It's so good to be here with you. Uh
we've missed being here with you for the
last two weeks, but we've been doing
lots of big things in our families.
We've had great uh celebrations uh going
on um in our family and Dr. White's
family. We've had three graduations. His
daughter, our daughter, and my husband
also graduated. So, we've been doing
lots of things. Um, and just been so
blessed by God. But we're so happy that
you are here with us, but we missed
being with you guys the last two weeks
and we're happy to be back. How are you,
Dr. White? I'm really good. It's
interesting how much we mirrored each
other because your daughter graduated
and your husband. I I I see you and I
hear you. I don't hear you. I see you.
So, I'm going to try to fix my audio so
I can I can hear you. Testing one, two,
three. Testing one, two, three. It's not
okay. I think if I see then if I turn
that up, I will echo. So, we don't want
that. Testing one, two, three. Testing
one, two, three.
Testing one, two, three. Right. Can you
talk again? Testing one, two, three.
Testing one, two, three. So,
I don't hear you. Okay. So maybe you can
say some welcomes to our audience while
I'm trying to figure out how I can hear
you. No problem. No problem. Well, well,
I do want to say welcome. Hopefully
Clint is here. Um but uh yeah, it's it's
interesting how much uh I mirrored uh
Sister Tante because her husband and
daughter both graduated and my wife and
my daughter uh both graduated. My my
wife earned her uh doctorate in nurse
practice and uh my daughter of course
got her bachelor's in uh public policy.
So yeah, it's it's it was amazing how
much we mirrored one another. Good to
see you Clint here. Um yeah, if you can
put in the chat where you are coming to
us from. Um of course I know Clint is
coming from
long long
something. Um but uh but but always a
pleasure, man. Always a pleasure to
interact with you. Uh let's see if you
can put in the chat where you're coming
from. We would really appreciate
that. Yeah, this is graduation season
and it is amazing how easy it is to see
a person graduating or see the high
points and say, "Hey, I want that." not
being aware or connecting to the
sacrifice, the toil, the difficulties,
the sweat, the tears that's involved in
that journey to get that thing that
you're really after. So, yeah, it's
absolutely um amazing. Long view, I knew
there was some longs. Yes, Clint. So,
long view and I believe it's Texas if
I'm not mistaken. All right, I see
Sharon Howard. Uh, greetings to you,
Sharon. and she is coming to us from
southern New Jersey. I wonder if you're
near the oranges cuz I know there's uh
there's some oranges in uh New
Jersey. Um let's see. Anybody else?
Um yeah. So yeah, we're here with Mental
Health Monday this uh this time and what
we're going to be talking about is we
are going to be doing questions and
answers. So, we so regret when like the,
you know, questions flood in at the end.
Um, so be sure that you get your
questions in the chat because we want to
be able to address as many of them as we
possibly can in the one hour that we're
going to be spending time together. Uh,
and have you noticed how quickly it
goes? So, we absolutely want to make the
most out of it. So, we are taking your
your your mental health questions and we
are committed to bringing as much value
to you as
possible. Uh, let's see. All right, we
got Crystal Cox from Spokane,
Washington. Hey, Crystal. I'm so glad
you could be with us.
Uh Crystal is a longtime uh member here
at uh Living Mana and it's definitely
great to see you. Great to see you um in
our chat in our midst and and benefiting
from the program. All right, let's see.
Um who is going to be that first person
with a question? Who's going to be that
first person with a question? Yeah. And
what a wonderful time we had um last
time we met uh where yeah we got some
really great questions. Questions about
communication
um boundaries often comes
up. Uh let's see. Yes. Can you hear me?
Yes, I can hear you. Okay, I can hear
you. I missed everything you said. So
all the welcomes all the welcomes that
Dr. White said to all of you and yeah,
we're thankful to be here. You do the
welcome way better than I do. That's for
sure. No, you were you were you were I
didn't hear you, but I you were smiling
and they're all here. So,
you did just fine. You did just fine. Um
Yes. And I saw Clint was here and I
said, "Hi, Crystal. I did hear you." As
soon as we turned on, I could hear you
again. You were saying, "Welcome Crystal
Cox." So, want to welcome you too,
Crystal. Great to see you here with us
this evening. Always good to see you.
So, I'm not sure if we have any
questions yet. I'm sure they're gonna We
do have a question. We have a question.
Yeah. He asked the questions. Have y'all
ever had any clients that just seemed as
if they couldn't be helped?
You know, Clint, you know what's really
funny about
this? I remember like there's certain
clients where what they
explained seemed so overwhelming
and you're like man I don't know how I
would handle
that but fortunately I asked the
question so hey what are you going to do
and they were able to immediately be
like well all I have to do is this this
this and then this this and this and
then we'll just take it um and then
we'll just take it from there. So the
the point being sometimes what might
seem as an impossibility to you to that
person they actually have a way of
dealing with it.
Um, Clint, to answer your question
explicitly, I have rarely if ever I
cannot remember a situation where I
walked out of the room just thinking
there's nothing that can be done except
of course if the person wouldn't
participate in the treatment or if they
rejected the treatment. That's the only
time there's nothing I can do is if they
won't participate. But as long as
they're willing to participate, I found
avenues to help them. What are your
thoughts, sister? I I agree with you and
that's been my experience as well. Um I
always tell my clients that you know
coming to their hour therapy appointment
um is just
um that's not where all the work is
done. It's when they go home and they
start, you know, putting in the work
that we talk about. um encouraging them
to to make whatever changes maybe or
taking some of the uh tools that we talk
about and actually implementing them
into their life on a daily basis and
being intentional about that. That's
where the work is done. That's where the
real hard work is done on a daily basis.
And so if they're not willing to do
those things or if they're just kind of
halfway doing them and not taking it
very seriously, then they can be helped
but they're just not doing what they
need to do. So that's been my
experience. And then on the other on the
flip side of that, I'm always so amazed
at those clients that are so good at
doing their homework or so good at doing
using the tools and I when they come
back, I'm just I'm thrilled for them
because they they're making changes.
Their change is happening pretty
quickly.
Yeah. Well said. Well said, Sharon.
Thank you for this question. How can
senior couples connect and keep their
finances in check?
Well, um I
think part of the answer is in the
question. Um because I think connecting
is a big deal. I don't know about you,
but I bet you anything you guys have
this nailed, you and Pastor Aore,
because you guys do your weekly dating,
right? And I think one of the things
that's easy for us to not do as couples,
especially when we're both super busy,
is a regular meeting time. Sharon, uh,
put a one in the chat if you and your
partner meet regularly, like especially
like once a week, a minimum of an hour.
Um, because that solves so many issues.
And if you treat it just like you would
your typical board meeting or business
meeting, then now you can divide it into
various factions.
you know, uh I I talk about the seven
vitals all the while. Well, it's just a
wonderful framework to comprehensively
approach your life
because now that meeting could address
all seven of those vitals and one of the
vitals is resources where you would talk
about finances.
And so with that regular meeting, I
think it's a it's a space for you to
deal with finances, make sure that
there's
alignment and and deal with the hiccups.
And here's the most important thing
about that. You're not now having these
crazy meetings when one spouse is
heading out the door. You know, like you
get these moments that are not conducive
to good communicating at all. Right?
Mhm. And if you're not meeting
regularly, you can get hijacked into
trying to solve issues in moments that
are really not conducive to congruency,
alignment, and moving forward as a
couple. What are your thoughts, Sister
Tante? Yeah. Um, you know, it I also
like to share u what Dr. John Gottman um
talks about. He uh talks about a weekly
business meeting. Um and again if you've
been a part of a of a church or on a on
a well any actually all the members can
come to the business meeting right but
he talks about a weekly business meeting
that the couples uh that thrive and are
successful in their marriages they have
the weekly date nights but they also
have the weekly business meeting and it
I just thought about what you said when
about when to when to talk about these
things. So the weekly business meeting
is really talking about all the
administrative things of the home that
it takes to run the home and family. So
you're talking about, okay, when this
bill is going to be paid or what the
children have to do or the dog has to go
to the vet checkup or, you know, I'm
just administrative things of whatever
about the home. So that when you're
together, that's when all that's
discussed and you talk about all those
things that are going to happen in that
week. Then when you spend time together,
you're actually not having to talk about
all the business stuff because you've
already done that. So you can spend that
quality time just spending great time
with your spouse, talking about your
passions and funny things and connecting
and all of those things, not business
stuff. So that's helpful for seniors and
for actually everybody for every
marriage. Um because we we we can tend
to
um become we are partners. When you get
married, it is your partner, but you can
become almost like business partners and
and just doing business stuff. And when
you see each other, you're just talking
business stuff and not, you know, the
passionate stuff and how much you love
each other and just having fun and maybe
making dinner together or taking a walk
and talking about the beautiful things
and not the stressful things. like
there's a time for that. So, just really
carving out a time to talk about those
things and a time to connect, which are
those weekly date nights. So, hopefully
that answers her question. Yeah, let us
know if that answered your
question. All right, Keith is asking the
question, "Hi, what do you do when
someone doesn't accept something as
truth? Obvious, objective, verifiable
truth. For example, grass does not
exist."
Um, if we were in a therapy session or
even a coaching session, I'd be like,
"Keith, tell me more about that." Right.
Yeah. Really to unpack that. Unpack it.
Like, say more about that. And And
really giving Keith an opportunity to
explain. Hey, wouldn't it be cool if we
could bring people on live? I would I've
thought about that. Let's talk let's
talk about that off air so we can really
maybe that will be season the first the
beginning of season 4 I think since
after the summer break let's talk about
it because I think that really would be
cool that would be really cool um I want
to ask I just want to say to follow up
with Keith um or really just to say that
if you know you can't control this
person you can't control other people so
unfortunately this friend or this person
that you know doesn't want to believe uh
truth, there's really nothing you can do
about that. Um you don't have the power
to to to change them. Um and so I
wouldn't waste a lot of your my time and
energy on that. You can pray for people
to to grow in areas that they need to
grow. Um and yeah, like Dr. White said,
if we were in therapy, I'd ask you more
questions. But just just off of what you
just said, um I would say let them be
who they are and pray for them to help
that they will realize that the grass is
green. Yeah, I would I would need more
details to comment on that. For sure.
For sure. Jason said, "If a person
doesn't feel connection with any human,
should they stay
single?" I I can't wait to hear what
your thoughts are on this. Um cuz on a
controversial level, Ellen
White
mentions there are some people who
should not get married.
Well, and I I think it's something
people people kind of
approach dating as if
everyone is kind of made for marriage
when in fact there are some people who
according to Ellen White anyway are like
unsuitable for marriage. Now that I
don't know what the context where she
was coming from. I'd have to read that
quote. But but but but go ahead. I'm
gonna let you finish. Go ahead. Go
ahead. Continue. Well, well, whether you
agree with her or not, Mhm. the bottom
line is you should devise your own
criteria for how much connection do you
need. So, if you check in with yourself,
you're going to see that you need two
things along the realm of this
connection. You need time to connect
with yourself.
You need time to connect with that other
person. Um, that other person needs time
to connect with you and that other
person also
needs time for themsel, never mind time
with other people and all that other
kind of stuff. And you you have to
determine what is the equation that will
work for
you. So obviously there will be
equations that will not work for you. M
some people you're going to see how much
time they need to spend with themsel
alone with family and friends with their
job and you're going to make the
decision you know what I need more time
other people they would be so smothering
that you'd be like you know I need more
space
and so I I just want you to see
that whether or not there's some humans
that should stay single the bottom line
is when you establish your criteria,
there will it will be pretty
clear who fits and who doesn't.
Um, so
yeah, again, I can't go off that quote
because I haven't read it for myself and
I know you read it, but I would love to
see the context of what she was saying
there. Sure. However, I would say
um
that I
think a lot of people who do get married
have not done the work on themselves to
be prepared for marriage. That's why
there's so many issues. And when I say
that, I mean there are so many traumas
from our past that haven't been dealt
with and from both partners, right? And
then they get married and then they find
out like this is so hard. I have, you
know, and then they find out, you know,
all my issues that I've had all all
throughout my life, like they're really
so prominent now that I'm here in
marriage. And so it was never dealt
with. So, I would say
that for this person, if you have a hard
time connecting to um well, here it says
with any human. So, definitely if you
have a hard time connecting with any
human um those are your words and and
you have a hard time with emotions and
things like that and sharing those
emotions or even receiving maybe
positive emotions back from another
person. I'm not sure. We don't have the
details, but I definitely would want
anyone that is feeling that way. And if
you're feeling that way, Jason, I would
love for you to meet with a mental
health professional because there's a
reason for that. Like you like God gave
us emotions and feelings to connect.
Like we're not There's a My husband's
Jamaican, so my my Jamaican
mother-in-law always says like no man is
an island. Meaning you weren't meant to
be by yourself. And God didn't mean for
us to be by ourselves. And I'm not
saying I'm not here to say every I don't
can't say it's God's will that every
single person be married. I'm not saying
that. But if you're having a hard time
connecting to people in general, um he
doesn't want you to be alone. Like uh he
didn't want Adam to be alone. So he
created Eve. Um and we have we have all
of these emotions and feelings that God
gave us and created in us not to not
connect with people. So I think that you
know talking with a mental health
professional to just see where that
comes from um and how you know just
talking to them more about that would be
very beneficial there to say there is a
personality type called skitsoid
personality if I'm not mistaken it's
skitsoid right it's a cluster this is a
cluster C um personality where these are
people who love to be alone they love to
be alone these are people who like for
example They love the night shift. Um,
and again, it's a it's a personality
disorder, but it's called skitsoid. I
believe it's skitsoid. It's been so long
since I've, you know, seen this, right?
But, you know, they and sometimes they
do their job so well like they might get
a promotion and now have to deal with
people and then that's when things kind
of unravel because they love being
alone. So, this is not to discount what
Sister Tante just said because we were
made God when we're functioning and
everything is normal, we were made for
relationship. That's true. But Sister
Tante, I found the Ellen White quotes.
Well, I'm glad you found it. So, this is
messages to young people and she writes
as follows. There are persons who have
not been trained to
self-denial and who are so full of their
own plans that they have no room for the
plans of others. Such persons should not
marry. Now, now that right there makes
sense. It kind of goes with what I was
that makes sense right there because
they haven't dealt with their stuff. So,
okay, go ahead. That that makes sense.
That's messages to young people page
452. Now in the Adventist home she
writes there are persons who have no
idea what constitutes a true home. They
are not prepared to marry. They would
bring into the marriage relation their
unambiable traits of character. The
Adventist home page 44.
So those both those both of those
together are I understand where she was
coming from there. But I ag but my point
still stands that those two things they
think things things can change like they
they may not know now or like what you
like to say until until now like you
know I mean if they if they become aware
and realize I think like what Jason was
saying like hey I just don't connect to
people very well and he goes and gets
the help and the healing he that story
can change. Do you see what I'm saying?
even those who don't understand how to
like Ellen White was saying how to have
a healthy home that can change too. you
can learn that. You know what I'm
saying? It's not like, well, you don't
know it, so this is an impossibility.
But, um, but it makes sense what she was
saying now. The quote makes sense now,
for sure. And Jason probably wasn't
asking for himself. He was asking for
Yeah. I'm not Maybe it wasn't for Jason.
He was asking for a friend. So, just
FYI. Um, but uh but no, no, you like you
said, Sister Tant, you said a lot of
times people are not necessarily
prepared. And what you're opening up the
door for is that with preparation, maybe
then they become suitable. All right.
Now, I'm going to put up this
firecracker. Uh, my
friends just my my friend just passed
away and her aunt is causing a ton of
drama in the family. Sincer's
condolences to you um as a result of the
passing of your your friend. Sincer's
condolences. And you said her aunt is
causing a ton of drama in the family.
She's being manipulative, greedy,
controlling, and a bulldozer to
everyone. How can they navigate through
her
behavior? This is where the book
boundaries, I think, is just so vital.
Two books I would think about. Number
one is
boundaries
because it it's it's always the same
thing. You're you're always looking at
making sure that your boundaries aren't
violated. Have you drawn your
boundaries? Have you educated the person
about the boundaries as well as
identified what the consequences are for
violating the boundaries and then
exercising them? Obviously within the
extent of the law.
And then the other book that's I think
helpful in these kind of situations is
the book Crucial Conversations. crucial
conversations when the stakes are high.
Um, I I think it can be incredibly uh
helpful
to understand how best you can you can
you can set boundaries but then have
those conversations and maintain them in
a productive zone.
Um, you know, clearly sometimes people
are misdirecting their grief in in a
less than productive fashion. And so
sometimes just, you know, kind of
putting your arm around the person and
saying, "Hey, what what is what are you
experiencing? How are you experiencing
this can be
tremendously helpful?" Um, what are your
thoughts, sister? Yeah.
Um, you know, I just looking here, she
is being manipulative, greedy,
controlling, and a bulldo bulldozer to
everyone. Um, and so you're right,
boundaries
meaning the boundaries is to not like
you can give somebody so much room to
get so close to you to even be able to
control. You know, it sounds this is a
auntie, right? And these are other
adults.
So what is you know you you if you set a
boundary you can like almost like push
her back some like she doesn't have
direct access to you. Um and then
there's a book by Mel Robbins. I don't
know if I mentioned it here but it's a
new book that she put out and it's
entitled let them. And I just thought it
makes so much sense. It's so simple
meaning when let them meaning the family
can't control her. They're not going to
change her from being controlling or
manipulative and being a bulldozer,
right? But once she realizes that the
family is not she's not getting the rise
or the reaction or you know any of that
from
them, what drives her to be that way is
not going to be um as she's not going to
be as motivated to be that way to make
it simple. Um, and so instead of
stressing out about, you
know, all of her behav behaviors, set a
boundary and in your mind mentally just
say, "Let her." Like, I can't, you can't
control her. Like, what are you going to
do to you can't control her you can just
set a boundary, make your mental state
and mind u be at peace. Um, and that's
not an easy thing to do. And this is a
difficult time because it's a grieving
time. Just lost a loved one.
But not allowing um someone that you
cannot control to just like they say
take space take or or take space in your
your mind and you're wasting all this
time and you're not even able to control
or stop them. It's a waste of time. I
would just say let her but set
boundaries so she can't get so close to
you. That was what I would say to that
family.
You get the last word on that question.
All right. Um, so this is from
Deborah Hailing. Everybody feels some
level of depression at certain periods
in their life. How do you know when it
becomes serious and help is needed?
You want to take the first step or you
want? Well, I was going to say there's a
criteria to for for someone to be
diagnosed with um major depression
disorder. And you have to, you know, you
have to have those feelings of um just
feeling, you know, just so sad that it's
hard to get out of bed, hard to take
care of yourself, like hygienewise, or
just just have no um just no just no
care, just don't have desires to do
anything. And if that sadness lasts
longer than two weeks, then you're
considered to have major depression
disorder. And so, um, I would definitely
reach out to want to talk to a mental
health professional if you're
experiencing something similar to what I
described.
Okay. Um, yeah. So the the idea being
that I would pay attention to function
and
so you if your mood is so from time to
time something will happen and your mood
of course will be down but you can still
function. Uh the symptoms often they're
short-lived they're contained but you
can still get out of bed you can still
go to work. you can still do the various
activities of daily living that we need
to do as humans. So when we're talking
about a clinical depression,
um it's the person now being
debilitated. They can't get out of bed.
All right? They're not attending to
hygiene. Um they're what
else? What else? they are um uh
sometimes progressively thinking about
harming themselves. Things are getting
so bad. So so function and severity of
the symptoms are what determines
um whether you need to get clinical
attention. Um so that that's the big way
that I would simplify it. And then
Deborah came back with a follow-up
question and she said, "Why is it when a
person is depressed, why does light,
whatever type, seem to bother them?" Um,
you want to take a stab at that? I'm
sorry. Okay. Um, why when a person is
depressed, why does
light Okay. Why does light whatever type
seems to bother them? Like sun. You're
talking to Deborah. I'm sunlight. You're
talking about sunlight. when you're
saying
light, you know, I can't hear you, Dr.
White.
Okay. What? Say that. Say that again.
Okay. I'm sorry. Okay. So, I'm I think
I'm a little confused on a question. It
says, "Why when a person is depressed,
why does light, whatever type, seem to
bother them?" So, I'm guess you're
talking about like the light like sun
sunlight and lights in the room, those
type of things.
Um, I'm gonna take a a stab at this
like, um, I know that when I'm working
with clients with depression, um, I have
a client now and it's a tellaalth, so I
can tell like they're in their room and
at the first session the room was dark,
like the blinds were down and the the
shades were closed, you know, they just
didn't bring a lot of sunlight in. And I
said, you know, one of the things that I
want you to do is I want you to open
those blinds every day to bring um light
into light into the room. And I would
say like their mood of depression makes
them want to be so much in the dumps
that they don't even want sunlight to
come into their room. Like it's just
that that's too much of a happy looking
thing and they just don't feel the
emotion of happiness. Um, but I believe
that when we are depressed, definitely
getting outside, getting fresh air,
walking, getting sunlight, that all
helps with our our state of our
emotions. I mean, it's not doesn't fix
it all. It doesn't fix it, but it's it's
a component that can help when you're
feeling down and sad,
right? So, uh, great question, Deborah.
Um, I'm going to piggyback off of what,
um, Sister Tante just mentioned. So
there can be sensory sensitivity. Um
depression can heighten your sensitivity
to stimula like light. Um especially ma
major depressive disorder with
melancholic features atypical depression
or if it's comorbid with anxiety. Um
depression often involves disregulation
of the autonomic nervous system. So
that's um the sympathetic and the
parasympathetic nervous system. So
bright light can worsen symptoms like
headache, eye strain, dizziness and and
even like
irritability. Depression can also
classically be associated with fatigue
and sleep disruption. So a depressed
individual can often suffer from
insomnia or hyperomnia. They'll have
poor sleep quality, but their circadian
rhythm can be thrown off. And um when
you're sleepdeprived or biologically
misaligned then um even moderate light
can be harsh or draining. It's like
being in light is kind of draining and
the person's already kind of energy
deplete. And then remember there's also
seasonal affective disorder confusion.
So when light therapy um so it's true
that light therapy can be a treatment
for seasonal affect disorder but at the
same time some depressed individuals
initially feel worse when exposed to
bright light and uh again this might be
due to their misalignment of their
biological
clock. And then last but not least, um
there can be some comorbid conditions uh
that occur uh with depression. Things
like migraine,
um uh things like post-traumatic stress
disorder. So there can be quite a
variety of reasons as to why people
experience um or have a difficult time
with bright light.
Good question. Thank you, Deborah.
Oh, that one went that one went away. I
was reading and it went away. What? Uh,
oh, there was another question by Sherry
Love, I think. Um, okay. Do you have any
techniques or books
recommended? Okay. Do you have any
techniques or books to recommend helping
someone whose family of origin has
caused self-doubt in the way one
perceives things to be? Man, can you
imagine a family that has not
contributed to self-doubt?
Right. I was just trying to think of a
book, but I can't think of a specific
book that hones in just on that. I don't
know. Do you, Dr. White?
Um, you know, of course, the book
Codependent No More, right, is is kind
of jumping into my mind. Mhm. Um but in
dealing with self-doubt,
you know, Mel Mel Robbins kind of writes
about that and uh
Bren Bnee Brown, I think, you know, they
might have some good content on how to
deal with self-doubt as I Yeah. And um
emotional focus therapy. I don't know
why my her name is based on Susan
Johnson. Yeah. Susan Johnson. Just
understanding the attachment theories.
um I think could also help um with that
as well.
Um has some good stuff in there. So
Sherry Belove um you can look up all of
those names that we mentioned and see
what they have um out there and if any
of those books that were mentioned would
help
um especially when you're talking about
family of of origin.
Um yeah. Right. And then last but not
least, of course, it's worth mentioning
scripture. I mean, because I think
scripture is one of the most powerful
tools to to validate you um remembering
that you're a child of a king.
Uh whether it's the proverbs that helps
you to balance
um self like valuing yourself but at the
same time not being arrogant. Uh so
yeah, I I think scripture and one's
faith can be really helpful in in in
reminding us to not have um self-doubt.
God has not given us a spirit of fear,
but a spirit of power and a sound mind.
That's some solid content.
Crystal, amazing question. Um great
question. Great question. Great
question. Um um yeah this there is
no this is it we can't give a cookie
cutter answer to this because everyone
is different and and is in a different
space and their time frame is different
um as far as like how quickly they they
heal from the loss of a spouse.
[Music]
Um, but I would say this, everybody's
different. Um, but I still highly,
highly, highly recommend, unfortunately,
my, you know, my sister-in-law, she's a
a young um, a young widow. And I I have
another really good friend who just lost
her husband about five, six weeks ago.
Um, and so I'm very well, I'm familiar
with you, Crystal, and I'm very familiar
with their uh, situation. So I would
what I would um recommend to anyone um
is to take your time. There is no time
to be like it has to be okay you're at a
year point so you're fine now. Like it
could be that you're at a year point and
you're you know that's okay. like
everybody is different but you
definitely I would encourage anyone in
that situation any widow any widower
would to take their time um because
grief is just it's uh just so such a
powerful thing that um is always it's
always it's fluid. It's always moving
and it it it can it can surface in in
different areas. It it goes in different
ways for different people. People grieve
differently. And so giving you yourself
that time to fully grieve um and and to
be in a healthy space. And really each
individual should know if especially
when they're working with a mental
health professional. And that's what I
would suggest to anyone who has lost a
spouse to work with a mental health
professional because you want to be in a
healthy space with your grief before you
could start considering uh dating. Let
let me let me ask the question this way
and hear your comment, Terry. What are
the dangers of starting to date too
soon?
Yeah, you're you're not you if you're if
you try to date too soon and you're not
healed in a healthy space with your
grief, then you're going to bring that
trauma into this um new relationship.
And what what would that look like?
It could it can look I don't know. It
can look a lot of ways.
Um you I mean if you're not you could
choose the wrong person. You could
choose the wrong person. Right. True.
You could choose the wrong person. You
can think that
[Music]
um their presence is you know their
presence or you know is helping you get
over the grief. But I feel like you
should that shouldn't be dependent upon
a person that you should uh be in a
healthy space because you
have kind of worked through the grief um
with I I believe with a therapist or a
mental health professional and then this
person just comes into your life and
they're like a cherry on top. You know
what I'm saying? It's not like you're
dependent upon them to be happy and to
not grieve your spouse as much because
that just that just isn't the healthy
space because that person can go away.
They can leave. They can be gone and
then you're just going to be right back.
So yeah, but back to your point, you can
definitely choose um the wrong person
because you're just using them to kind
of cover up the pain.
So exactly well said, Sister Tante. And
I I just felt like if we we can't give
you what is too soon, but we can tell
you the dangers of too soon. Danger
number one is ultimately you could
choose the wrong person. And a a lot of
times when we choose the wrong person,
it's chosen from the platform of fear of
loneliness.
So the pain of being alone could drive
you to choose the wrong person. And
let's drill down a little bit more.
Ultimately,
people people will give you their
warning signs.
People will advertise their red flags.
The question is, are you in a mental
state to detect them, right? And that's
part of this too soon part. When if
you're dating too soon, you can't even
detect the um the red flags. I don't
know about you, but I I don't know if
you've ever been driving and you've been
driving too long. There's a point
where your brain isn't processing the
information that's coming in.
Your eyes are open.
You're you're you're
awake, but you're so tired. you're not
as responsive as normal to the
information that's coming in. And that's
the that's the danger that a widow might
be vulnerable to, right?
And um and this is for Crystal and
anyone else when you're and yes when
when you're having children, young
children in in the situation, you have
to be even more careful on how you're
moving forward when you're doing that.
So just saying that in general to
anyone. So and so that was just one
thing is like you might end up choosing
the wrong person. You haven't healed. um
you
you some of the some of the things that
issues you might have had with a past
partner, now you're projecting onto this
new partner, right? Um and if the
relationship was formed when you had
this need, heaven forbid, now you heal
and you're like, I don't need this
relationship. Like, I don't know what
was going on when I formed it.
So again, we don't know what too soon
is, but we do know the dangers of too
soon. And those were just a few, right?
Um, to answer that question, great
question, Crystal. It was a great
question question. And Veronica, thank
you because and I don't know why that
book didn't pop into my head. I I
recommend that book to my clients all
week. But this is for Deborah's
question. Um, Veronica said, "The Body
Keeps score could also be um a good
book. It does deal with trauma
specifically, but the person, you know,
that Deborah asking the question, the
person could be going through, there's
pieces in there that could definitely
help um with family of origin issues
because usually there's trauma with
family of origin stuff." Um,
okay. So May said, "Is it normal for
individuals in a relationship and now
about to get married to talk all their
wing hours?" Talk all day. Oh boy, do I
remember those days. Normal for two
individuals.
I remember those days. You remember
those days where you would talk into
They talk about the the wedding all the
time. Is that what is that? Is that what
she is that what this No, no. I think
it's talking into the sunrise. Like you
talk so long. Oh, okay. Okay. Goodness,
I totally missed that, guys. I was on an
early flight this morning. I think I'm
tired. Okay. Okay. It's normal. Okay.
Yeah. Um Yeah. Yeah. All it's it's kind
of it's kind of a sign of
infatuation. And it's really cool. I got
to tell you, man, it is so cool when you
continue to enjoy your partner past this
honeymoon phase, right? Like you just
really like talking to each other. You
like being with each that's such a
beautiful thing. Yeah. You don't like
you don't enjoy not being with them. Of
course, you have to not be with them at
times, work and different things, but
you enjoy being with them. Yeah. This is
You're right. after the infatuation
stage that should continue. It's funny
something happened to my husband and I
cuz this because we did used to talk um
in the early early just getting to know
each other till like 2 3 in the morning.
We were talking on the phone and
just yeah that would happen. We'd get to
know each other on the phone. Um but it
was this just this past weekend uh we
were somewhere in um actually going to
see my father-in-law. He's um in a
nursing home. we were going to visit and
um I think we were holding hands and the
walking down the hallway and and this
lady said, "Are you guys newly married?"
And we
said I said, "No, not at all." She's
like, "But you're you're holding hands."
Like, "Oh, well, we like to hold hands,
you know." Um but anyways, it's just,
you know, you should always still date
your spouse. That's my point. Like,
Amen. Yeah. Always. Amen. Well said.
Well said. But that that's beautiful
when you can preserve what I called
virgin love. That's just that's just
beautiful. Yes. Beautiful.
All right. We're still uh getting more
getting more questions. But just to just
to where that kind of the reason why
that kind of stood out to me when that
lady said that is when we were first
married, we had just been married a few
months and we were at a large church
event camp meeting. Like so any all the
Adventists here know what camp meeting
is, but and um we were holding hands and
walking around or something and and this
one gentleman said, "You guys are and
then we really were newly married." He
was like, "You guys have just gotten
married." We're like, "Yeah, within the
last year." And he said, "You won't be
holding hands like that, you know, many
years down the road or whatever." And
then we made a mental note to be like,
"We're always going to hold hands no
matter what." And you know, this is the
camp meeting we were at for years. Like
we would visit like once a year and we
would run in to this gentleman and then
we would still hold hands right in front
of him so we could say, "See, we're
still holding hands."
Yeah. I mean, so anyway, absolutely. All
right, we got more questions here. My
husband calls me from work 52 times a
day after seven years of marriage, so we
still talk throughout the day. Yeah. Uh
that's called being in love, Amra, just
in case you didn't realize that. That is
That is
uh Let me see. Veronica for you,
Veronica. 35 years of marriage and we
still hold hands. That's great. That's
beautiful. That's beautiful. That is
beautiful. Um Florence and I still hold
hands. I will definitely That's what
That's wonderful. Yeah, still hold
hands. Computer froze. Thank you for
your supportive comments. All right.
Ammer says,
let's see. How soon is too soon? We
already addressed that.
Yeah, great relationship uh questions.
Great questions overall. We're almost
out of time, but we're we have enough
time to take a few more uh questions.
Well, let's see. Maybe All right, two
more two more questions. Let's see who's
going to be that person to ask that
question.
These have been great questions though.
Absolutely. No, Crystal, thank you for
sharing what you shared and it's it's
quite a journey. Um, but yeah, you're
you're definitely giving yourself time
to evolve.
Um, and yes, absolutely. When you're
dealing with a family unit, that that
that's part of it as well. Mhm. Um once
in a while you'll see children who are
in a sense kind of forbidding the parent
to move on, if you will. Yeah. And
that's
I just I just don't think it's the
children's place at that point. I'm not
and I'm talking about grown children.
Right. Right. Right. And it's definitely
not their place. No, definitely not.
Definitely not. But I um you know, it's
definitely not their place. It's not.
Um, let's see. We had some questions.
Barring things like cognitive decline
and fearing that the person's going to
be exploited or something like that.
Barring those or if the person is just
really a bad person and you're like,
"Hey, mom, dad, that's not a good
person." But besides that, okay,
Veronica, how do you
respond to to family when they accuse
you of loving loving your deceased
husband's family more than you love
them?
H how do you respond to family when they
accuse you of loving you? So I guess the
deceased family of this family, they
feel like you love those who have passed
more than
them. Well, I'm that is that's a very uh
unique situation, but
um
again sometime again you can't control
the what people you can't control what
people think. you can only control how
you respond. Um, and you know, speaking
the truth to them. I mean, if you
genuinely do like them and love them,
you remind them how you do love and
appreciate them and you show that to
them. But again, if they can't take that
and understand that and accept that,
then there's nothing you can't do,
right? Because you can't go on them and
make them accept your love and
appreciation and respect that you do
have for them. Maybe they're
just I don't know for whatever reason
not willing to believe uh what you're
saying or they don't they're not your
actions for some reason they're not
believing your actions that are showing
that you do care and love for them.
Yeah, it's a very unique um situation.
Um if someone that's in that Yeah,
there's there's definitely limits at
times. Um but you're you're bringing to
mind concept. Don't get furious, get
curious. Don't get furious, get curious.
And what I mean by that is I would
really
utilize this as an opportunity to find
out as much information as possible
about why they feel the way they do,
right? You know, here's this
accusations. Hey, so you feel like I
love my deceased husband's family more
than I love you. Tell me more about
that. That's that's such of an important
tell me more about that. And I and I
mean give them a chance to really
articulate where they're coming from and
exhausted, you know, and just really
hear them out. At
minimum, you might walk away with some
clarity as to what they're thinking and
where the derangement is taking place,
but at least you'll have absolute
clarity. And at
maximum, you might be able to pinpoint
and speak with pinpoint precision as to
what might help them gain some clarity.
That's at maximum. There's no guarantee,
but at least you'll walk away being
really clear about where they're coming
from. Um, and being able to say, "Hey, I
can at least see why you're thinking
that way. I don't necessarily agree, but
at least I can see where you're coming
from. Um, and then you can at least take
it from there. When we have clarity,
then we can have movement. Um, but where
there's obscurity, opacity, um,
translucency, like when when we can't
see, it's hard to make movements. It's
hard to make decisions. It's hard to
draw conclusions.
I There's a question that's not on there
that I want to answer next, and that's
this one. and this one that I'm looking
at. But um do you can answer the one you
can answer frankly speaking how do I
prepare for single life after 30 years
of marriage and then I'm going to take
okay how do I prepare for single life
after 30 years of marriage? Um
frankly one of the problems that we
struggle with as humans is valuing the
phase that we're in. Mhm. A lot of
married people are looking forward to
being single. A lot of single people are
looking forward to being married. Uh
employed people can't wait to retire and
unemployed people can't wait to get a
job. It's it's just this incessant
inability to
appreciate the moment that you're in.
So with that said,
frankly, if you're looking
at single life, it might help to
remember some of the things you
sacrificed as a result of 30 years of
marriage. Um, no question there are
positive aspects of being married, but
it does require some sacrifice. It does
require on some level muting your
personality.
My wife, for example, can't stand it
when I'm listening to music really loud.
Well, but I like listening to it. And
I'm not even talking about super loud.
But unless of course it's her song, then
she likes it loud. Yeah. Then she's
like, "That's my jam." Huh. Then she
likes she likes it loud. But but the
point is being there are times where you
mute an aspect of yourself that now in
your single life you can revisit that.
Some people were wanted to be more
artistic. They wanted to travel more. Uh
they wanted to nurture a pursuit or a um
hobby. Well, now you can step into that.
You can embrace it and and you can
absolutely enjoy it. So frankly, the the
goal would be, look, I'm going to try to
avoid making the mistake of not valuing
the phase that I'm in, and I'm going to
make the most of it.
As it aligns with your values and all
and morals and all this other kind of
stuff.
Good, good answer. Good question. Um,
so,
um, Dakara has a question which is a
great question.
Is is it wrong to date outside of your
faith? Do they have to be uh Seventh Day
Adventists? Why is it frowned upon in
the church to marry outside of our faith
if they are believers in
Christ? So great question. Um the Bible
talks I see you Takara trying to start
some trouble here.
So, no. So, you know, the Bible talks
about not being unequally yolked, and
you're saying, "Well, hey, they're a
Christian. We both believe in Jesus, and
that's fantastic. That's great." Um,
however, there's more in the Bible than
um I mean, Jesus teaches some principles
that are not
um adhered to by by everyone. So, like
let's just say, so the person you want
to date that's not that's not a Seventh
Day Adventist. Um, and um, okay, there's
so many there's so many ways that we can
talk about this. Like, let's just say if
they're young um, and you're and they're
you're young and you haven't had
children yet, so you're going to have
children together and grow this family
together. And so you want to go to
church, you're going to go to church on
the Sabbath, and you know, this person's
going to go to church um on Sunday,
which it's not a sin to go to church on
Sunday, but you know, you're trying to
what are you representing to your
children? What are you teaching your
children? It's very confusing to the
children. Um then
there's, you know, if you're a Seventh
Day Adventist, you believe in this. You
believe the dead know nothing, right?
and maybe they believe they they can
talk to their dead grandmother who they
love so much who's in heaven now. You
know, there's all these different thing.
There's just so many different different
things. And then just practical. So like
you're wanting to keep the Sabbath at
home and you want it to just be pure
like 24 hours of just worshiping God.
And they're like, "No, the game is on,
so let let's turn on the football game."
I'm just I'm giving you real life
examples here. I mean, it's going to be
different in every situation. And that
just you know that it's going
to it can cause conflict within the
marriage. Are there people who have done
it and the other person they've done it
and the other person actually becomes
joins becomes a Seventh Day Adventist or
they of the same faith? That's fine too.
I wouldn't want somebody to to become um
a Seventh Day Adventist or I wouldn't
want them to become a Catholic or
anything because of the other person.
like you need to want to do what you're
doing because of your relationship with
God and not because of another person.
But there's just so many things. Those
were just small little examples I could
throw out there. It's really because
it's not that they're not true
Christians. It's not because they're bad
people by any means. It's just it's it's
difficult to operate a home um with two
different belief systems.
Well said, man. Well said. I I think
let's start the discussion with
Marriage is a 50% failure rate. Okay,
let's start there. That's already hard.
I like to start there. Okay. It's hard
when you do believe the same religion.
I'm I'm saying I'm saying like your
marriage by itself is a hard thing um
with a super high failure rate when you
think about it. Yeah. So given given the
stakes because if you if if the marriage
survives the legacy is so amazing the
protection offered to the children I
mean just amazing uh even the health
that's conveyed to both people more men
than women I'll grant you that but even
the health that's conveyed out of this
world right
um but with something so high stake and
yet so high risk, wouldn't you want to
do everything possible to increase the
likelihood of it
succeeding given how challenging it is?
And and then you come and then you come
at the issue of um 7th Day Adventist.
One of the things that's unique about
Seventh Day Adventism as a denomination
of
Christianity
is it is
peculiar. It is unusual.
Um, our approach to the Sabbath, it's
unique. I'm not talking about whether
it's right or whether it's wrong. It's
I'm just talking about what it is. From
a doctrinal
standpoint, it it is
something taxing how we approach
it. So, what that means then
is there's it's ripe for so much
conflict when a person approaches it in
a different way. Now that this is going
with what Sister Tante was listing, but
what I'm emphasizing is it's a 50%
marriage is a 50% failure rate.
Um, and the interesting thing is there
are some statistics though that when
there's increased
compatibility that failure rate actually
goes down.
So, um just some things that I would
want um to share.
Um just I think um um Teresa had you
might want to clarify a little bit that
when you were sharing about she's I
don't think well she I think she might
have missed well you might want to
clarify it a little bit after 30 years
of marriage our relationship you missed
that person that last thing you would
think
about what you couldn't do when you were
married I think she's saying like she's
been married 30 years she's not thinking
about wanting to be single or I don't
know. I I don't know if it's connected
to that. When you were saying married
people, they're not being when you were
talking about people not being hap happy
in their present situation. Everybody's
looking like married people want to be
single and single people want to be
married. Oh, no, no. Good, good, good
point. Like that that is in no way to
convey that you in particular, Teresa,
were unhappy while you're married. That
is no way to convey that. So, thank you
for giving me the chance to clarify
that. Yeah. Um, I was just using that as
an example of
how
sometimes we are we we don't enjoy a
situation as
much because we're distracted by what
could be. But that obviously is not true
for you, Teresa. Um, obviously is not
true for you in in your situation. It
seems like yeah, you loved all aspects
of marriage and now you would just use
that same talent and love aspects of
being single. I think if in fact, you
know, you you really did enjoy the
relationship, you know, the way I
believe that you did, I think you can go
forward
knowing your partner is thrilled to see
you happy even in this next phase. If if
if if the relationship is as rich as I
believe it was for you,
uh I'm I'm sure your
partner would want you to enjoy this
next phase. Much the same way, Teresa,
I'm sure you would want your partner um
uh to enjoy, you know, singleness. You
you would be sad to see them in some way
muting their experience. Um but no,
thank you for the opportunity to
clarify. Um no, not everybody is unhappy
in in marriage. In fact, there are a lot
of people who are very happy in
marriage. So, thanks for the opportunity
to clarify that. Yes. Just I think your
biggest point really is like learning
how to be happy um to be happy in the
present in the space that God has you in
at this at this time, right? not to look
over and be like, "Be happy with right
now." Married, single, this is where God
has you be happy. If I mean, there could
be things in the marriage that can cause
you to be unhappy. I get that. But yeah,
I think that's the general thing that
you were trying to say, too. All right.
So, well, we are all done for this
evening. Um, we want to thank you for
your questions. They were great. you
definitely um made you guys have great
questions and they were all just all
around like touching all different areas
and so um we just really appreciate your
questions. Hopefully by God's grace we
gave you uh good answers. He probably
gave you better answers today. I'm so
tired
today. I was on an early flight and then
came and worked and so yes, but um by
God's grace uh you were you were blessed
and so we want you to to share this.
Definitely share this link on your
social media. Uh people don't have to
watch it live. They can catch it after
and get they can't ask their questions,
but they can get some answers to maybe
questions they have as well. And um we
want to to see you guys. We will not be
here next week actually, but we will
return the week after that. However,
catch True Health Tuesday because uh Dr.
Maria will will be here uh with you guys
on Tuesday. you don't want to miss her
wonderful program to give you all those
uh wonderful tips on how to um eat a
healthy life and how you how what you
eat can actually be healing and helpful
to your body. So, you don't want to miss
that. But we want you right back here in
two weeks for another mental health
Monday. And we are just so thankful you
were with us and have a good evening.
God bless you.